Guide to the Samuel Harper Diaries 1849-1903
University of Chicago Library
Harper, Samuel. Diaries
1849-1903
2.25 linear feet (5 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
Samuel Harper (1823-1905), father of William Rainey Harper. The collection consists primarily of Harper’s diaries from 1864 to 1903, along with notes, clippings and receipts enclosed in the diaries. Also included in the collection is an expense book for the year 1862.
Information on Use
Access
The collection is open for research.
Biographical Note
Father of William Rainey Harper. Born April 29, 1823 in the vicinity of Canonsburg, Washington County, Pennsylvania. Moved with his family to a farm near New Concord, Muskingum County, Ohio about 1830. Married Ellen Elizabeth Rainey of Cambridge, Ohio. Five children were born to them, William Rainey, Samuel, Robert Francis, James and Mary. He died in Chicago at the home of his son William in July of 1905.
Scope Note
The collection consists primarily of Harper’s diaries from 1864 to 1903. Found in the pockets of the diaries were concert programs, advertisements, news clippings, correspondence, tax receipts, and notes. Also included in the collection is an expense book for the year 1862.
Related Resources
The following related resources are located in the Department of Special Collections:
http://www.lib.uchicago.edu/e/spcl/select.html
Subject Headings
Harper, Samuel, 1823-1905; Harper, William Rainey, 1856-1906
INVENTORY
- Expense account book, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 1864, Pocket Diary for Jan 1-Dec 31, 1864 Tax receipts, 1864 Ticket for drawing, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- 1865, Pocket Diary for Jan 1-Dec 31, 1865 Programs, ticket, notes, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- 1866, Pocket Diary for Jan 1-Dec 31, 1866 Check, 1866 Programs for Muskingum College, 1866-1868 Correspondence about the Golden Dwarf Peach, 1866 Business card for Alexander Caskey, "Presbyterian Witness," undated Business card for Anderson and Bronson, "Water Elevators," 1866 Reward of Merit for Samie Harper, undated Report card for William R. Harper, 1867 Cucumber seed packet, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- 1867, Pocket Diary for Jan 1-Dec 31, 1867 Notes, undated Concert programs, undated Advertisement for Magic Paste, undated Newspaper clipping, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- 1868, Pocket Diary for Jan 1-Dec 31, 1868 Notes, undated Programs for Muskingum College, 1868 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- 1869, Pocket Diary for Jan 1-Dec 31, 1869 Tax receipts, 1869 Programs for Muskingum College, 1869 News clippings, undated Cucumber seed packet, undated Business card for Aaron McNeil, Attorney at Law, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- 1870, Pocket Diary for Jan 1-Dec 31, 1870 Tax receipts, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- 1871, Pocket Diary for Jan 1-Dec 31, 1871 Tax receipts, 1871-1872 Music program, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- 1872, Pocket Diary for Jan 1-Dec 31, 1872 Tax receipts, 1872 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- 1873, Pocket Diary for Jan 1-Dec 31, 1872 Tax receipts, 1873 Concert program, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
- 1874, Pocket Diary for Jan 1-Dec 31, 1874 Pocket Diary for Jan 1-March 19, 1874 Tax receipts, 1873 The Index, 1874 Business card, G.W. Perkins, undated Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
- 1875, Pocket Diary for Jan 1-Dec 31, 1875 Tax receipts, 1875 Calling card, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
- 1876, Pocket Diary for Jan 1-Dec 31, 1876 Tax receipts, 1875 Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
- 1877, Pocket Diary for Jan 1-Dec 31, 1877 Correspondence and notes, 1877 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- 1878, Pocket Diary for Jan 1-Dec 31, 1878 Advertisements, 1878 Tax receipts, 1878 Program from Muskingum College, 1857 Notes, undated Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
- 1879, Pocket Diary for Jan 1-Dec 31, 1879 Tax receipts, 1879 Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
- 1880, Pocket Diary for Jan 1-Dec 31, 1880 Tax receipts, 1880 Notes, undated Legal information, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
- 1881, Pocket Diary for Jan 1-Dec 31, 1881 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- 1882, Pocket Diary for Jan 1-Dec 31, 1882 Tax receipts, 1882 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- 1884, Pocket Diary for Jan 1-Dec 31, 1884 Tax receipts, 1884 Postcard, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
- 1885, Pocket Diary for Jan 1-Dec 31, 1885 Tax receipts, 1885 Correspondence and notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
- 1887, Pocket Diary for Jan 1-Dec 31, 1887 Tax receipts, 1887 News clippings, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
- 1888, Pocket Diary for Jan 1-Dec 31, 1888 Tax receipts, 1887 News clippings, undated Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
- 1889, Pocket Diary for Jan 1-Dec 31, 1889 Tax receipts, 1887 News clippings, undated Correspondence, 1887 Calling card, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
- 1890, Pocket Diary for Jan 1-Dec 31, 1890 Tax receipts, 1890 News clippings, undated Correspondence, 1890 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- 1891, Pocket Diary for Jan 1-Dec 31, 1891 Tax receipts, 1891 News clippings, undated Correspondence, 1891 Concert program, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
- 1892, Pocket Diary for Jan 1-Dec 31, 1892 Concert program, undated News clippings, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
- 1895, Pocket Diary for Jan 1-Dec 31, 1895 A note (possibly by Maime) dedicating the pocket diary which was a Christmas gift, undated Correspondence, 1896 Receipts, 1895 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- 1896-1897, Pocket Diary for Jan 1, 1896-Dec 5, 1897 Notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
- 1897, Pocket Diary for Feb 24, 1897-Dec 5, 1897 Notes, undated News clippings, undated Programs and advertisements, 1901 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- 1898, 1899, 1901, Pocket Diary for Dec 5, 1898-Jan 18, 1901 News clippings, undated Program and advertisement, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
- 1899-1900, Pocket Diary for Jan 13, 1899-Dec 22, 1900 News clippings, undated Advertisements, undated Notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
- 1901, Pocket Diary for Jan 1, 1901-Feb 27, 1901 News clippings, undated Notes, undated Invitation, 1901 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- 1903, Pocket Diary for Jan 1, 1903-Nov 10, 1903 News clippings, undated Blank bank draft, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Journal, May 1, 1849-December 27, 1863 (Box 5, Folder 1)